Macbeth Gallery
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Correspondence Files, 1838-1968, n.d., Series 1:; (Box 1-95, 163-164, OV 165; 96.2 linear feet)
  - Correspondence, 1838-1968, n.d., 1.1:
    - Worthen, Samuel Copp (2664), 1941 (Box 85)
    - Wright, Alice Morgan (2664), 1915-1916, 1926 (Box 86)
    - Wright, Cushing F. (2664), 1940-1947 (Box 86)
    - Wright, Fred W. (2664), 1918, 1927-1958, (2 folders) (Box 86)
    - Wright, Horace P. (2665), 1913-1922 (Box 86)
    - Wright, J. (2665), 1914 (Box 86)
    - Wright, Leititia E. (Mrs. W. R.; 2665), 1920-1921 (Box 86)
    - Wright, Marian H. (2665), 1917 (Box 86)
    - Wright, Martin W. (2665), 1932, 1937 (Box 86)
    - Wright, Nellie B. (NMc12), 1898 (Box 86)
    - Wright, William B. (2665), 1927 (Box 86)
    - Wuerpel, Edmund H. (NMc12/NMc16), 1904-1906 (Box 86)
    - Wuerth, Gustav C., 1915-1932 (Box 86)
    - Wuerth, Louis A. (2665), 1929-1937 (Box 86)
    - Wulbern, Edward N. and Mrs. Wulbern (2665), 1921-1924 (Box 86)
    - Wulling, Frederick J. and Lucile J. Wulling (2665), 1916-1932, 1947 (Box 86)
    - Wurts, Charles P. and Mrs. Wurts (2665), 1916-1918 (Box 86)
    - Wyant, A. H. (Alexander Helwig; 2665), 1866 (copy), 1892 (Box 86)
    - Wyant, A. L. (Mrs. A. H.) and Alex L. Wyant (NMc12/NMc16/2665), 1892-1915, 1932, n.d., (2 folders; includes illustrated letter 1902) (Box 86)
    - Wyatt, A. C. (2665), 1922 (Box 86)
    - Wyeth, Andrew (2665), 1937-1954, (8 folders; see also OV 165; includes illustrated letters 12/23/37, 9/20/50, 10/12/50, ca. 3/51, and 10/1/52 and marked-up copy of catalog for exhibition 11/52) (Box 86)
    - Wyeth, N. C. (Newell Convers; see also Wyeth, Andrew; 2665), 1914, 1941-1943 (Box 86)
    - Wyllie, G. Allan (2665), 1955-1956 (Box 86)
    - Wyman, James A. (2665), 1949-1950 (Box 86)
    - Wynne, Agnes (Mrs. Philip H.; 2665), 1924 (Box 86)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Illegible and Unidentified, ca. 1911 (Box 86)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wa-Walk, 1895-1951 (Box 86)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wall-Walw, 1895-1954 (Box 86)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wam-Wari, 1896-1947 (Box 86)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Warm-Wars, 1896-1951 (Box 86)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Was-Watr, 1893-1949 (Box 86)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wats-Way, 1903-1952 (Box 86)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wea-Weh, 1893-1947 (Box 86)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wei, 1893-1958 (Box 86)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wel-Wen, 1895-1951 (Box 86)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wer-Wes, 1895-1952 (Box 86)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wet-Wey, 1900-1954 (Box 86)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wha-Whita, 1895-1937 (Box 86)
    - W, Miscellaneous: White-Whitely, 1896-1955 (Box 86)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Whitfield-Why, 1896-1946 (Box 86)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wi-Wig, 1896-1957 (Box 86)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wilb-Wile, 1896-1947 (Box 87)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wilk-Wille, 1898-1952 (Box 87)
    - W, Miscellaneous: William-Willys, 1895-1950 (Box 87)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wilm-Wiltz, 1896-1953 (Box 87)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wim-Witt, 1896-1953 (Box 87)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wo-Won, 1903-1952 (Box 87)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wood-Woot, 1894-1951 (Box 87)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wor-Wra, 1913-1950 (Box 87)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wri, 1911-1956 (Box 87)
    - W, Miscellaneous: Wro-Wy, 1895-1957 (Box 87)
    - Yalden, J. Ernest G., 1932 (Box 87)
    - Yale University (2666), 1915, 1922-1956, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 87)
    - Yancey, Martha F. (Mrs. R. S.; 2666), 1923-1926 (Box 87)
    - Yardell, Enid, 1912 (Box 87)
    - Yates, Cullen (2666), 1911-1932 (Box 87)
    - Yates, J. William, Jr. (2666), 1926-1930 (Box 87)
    - Yeats, Jack Butler (NMc12/NMc16/2666), 1910, (includes illustrated letter 9/22/10) (Box 87)
    - Yeto, Gengiro (NMc12/NMc16), 1903 (Box 87)
    - Yetter, Lucy H. (2666), 1916 (Box 87)
    - Young, C. Jac (2666), 1929-1932 (Box 87)
    - Young, Charles Morris (NMc12/NMc16/2666), 1902-1922 (Box 87)
    - Young, Dorothy Weir and Mahonri M. Young (2666), 1914-1945, 1956 (Box 87)
    - Young, Edward Clinton and Elizabeth Young (2666), 1924-1946 (Box 87)
    - Young, Grace A. (2666), 1926-1930, 1950 (Box 87)
    - Young, J. W. and Mrs. Young (2666), 1905-1950 (Box 87)
    - Young's Art Shop (2667), 1924-1930 (Box 87)
    - Yunt Art Galleries (2667), 1922-1932, (2 folders) (Box 87)
    - Y, Miscellaneous: Ya-Young, J., 1899-1952 (Box 87)
    - Y, Miscellaneous: Young, M.-Yu, 1896-1952 (Box 87)
    - Zabriskie, Cornelius and Orlena A. Zabriskie (2667), 1914-1924, 1932, n.d. (Box 87)
    - Zanetti, Silvio (2667), 1937 (Box 87)
    - Zaugg, John L. (2667), 1926-1927 (Box 87)
    - Zell, Lucian M. (2667), 1924-1930 (Box 87)
    - Zens, Paul and Mrs. Zens (2667), 1925-1926, 1952 (Box 87)
    - Ziegler, Henry (2667), 1926-1932 (Box 87)
    - Ziegler, Samuel P. (Texas Christian University; 2667), 1919-1932 (Box 87)
    - Zilcken, Charles Louis Philippe (NMc12/NMc16), 1893-1896, (includes illustrated letter 9/23/96) (Box 87)
    - Zimmerman, M. W. (2667), 1925-1926 (Box 87)
    - Zimmermann, F. Ernst (2667), 1923, 1937 (Box 87)
    - Zinsser, William H. (2667), 1950-1952 (Box 87)
    - Zogbaum, F. (2667), 1939, 1944 (Box 87)
    - Zug, George B. (NMc21/2667), 1907-1920, 1930, 1943 (Box 87)
    - Z, Miscellaneous, 1907-1952 (Box 87)
    - Illegible Signatures and Unidentified Correspondents, 1893-1963, n.d., (3 folders; includes possible undated John Singer Sargent letter) (Box 87)
    - Correspondence Separated - Fragile (Box 163 (hol))
      - Art Institute of Chicago (NMc23/2568), 1916 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Arthur Ackerman & Son, Inc. (NMc22/2564), 1923 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Carnegie Institute (NMc31/NMc32/2577), 1916, 1923, (3 folders) (Box 163 (hol))
      - Carson Pirie Scott & Co. (NMc32/2578), 1915-1916, 1923 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Casson Galleries (NMc32/2578), 1923 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Chase, Frank Swift (NMc32/2578), 1916 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Cheney, Lilian F. (Mrs. B.; NMc33/2579), 1921-1923 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Church, Frederick Stuart (NMc5/NMc33/2579), 1915-1916, (includes 10 illustrated letters) (Box 163 (hol))
      - Cincinatti Museum Association (NMc33/2579), 1916 (Box 163 (hol))
      - City Club of New York (2580), 1916 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Clark, DeWitt A. (NMc33/2580), 1916 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Clarke, Thomas B. (NMc34/2580), 1916 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Cleveland Museum of Art (NMc34/2580), 1916 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Cochran, Allen D. (NMc34/2580), 1916 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Coffin, Edward Francis, (NMc34/2581) 1916 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Cole, Theodore A. (2581), 1916 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Columbia University and Alumni Club (2581), 1916 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Coman, Charlotte Buell (NMc5/NMc34/2582), 1916 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Curtis and Cameron Incorporated (NMc35/NMc36/2584), 1916 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Curtis, W. J. (NMc36/2583), 1916 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Dallas Art Association (NMc37/2584), 1916 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Dilworth, C. W. (2586), 1916 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Dougherty, Paul (NMc6/NMc43/2587), 1923 (Box 163 (hol))
      - du Pont, Alice (Mrs. T. Coleman; 2588), 1923 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Du Puy, Herbert (2588), 1923 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Durham, Knowlton (2588), 1923 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Duveneck, Frank B. and Mrs. Duveneck (2588), 1923-1925 (Box 163 (hol))
      - E, Miscellaneous (2588), ca. 1900-1950 (Box 163 (hol))
      - F. M. Dyer & Co., 1916-1922 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Fouke, Philip B. (2591), 1923 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Fox, Philip (2591), 1923 (Box 163 (hol))
      - Frank, Charles Lee (2591), 1923 (Box 164 (pam))
      - Frederick B. Thomason, Inc., Insurance (2645), 1912 (Box 164 (pam))
      - F, Miscellaneous (2589-2590), ca. 1900-1960 (Box 164 (pam))
      - Library of Congress 2582), 1916 (Box 164 (pam))
      - Macbeth Farm, 1923 (Box 164 (pam))
      - Salmagundi Club and Trainer and Associates (2632), 1936-1937 (Box 164 (pam))
      - Worcester Art Museum (NMc21/2664), 1912 (Box 164 (pam))
    - Oversized Material from Culver, Charles (2583), 1949 (Box OV 165)
    - Oversized Material from Wyeth, Andrew (2665), 1964, n.d. (Box OV 165)
  - Requests for Publications, 1893-1952, n.d., 1.2:
    This subseries contains requests for gallery publications such as Art Notes and Biographical Notes and catalogs for various exhibitions. Requests are often accompanied by a response from the gallery.
    Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by first letter of the correspondent's surname and chronologically by year.
    - A, 1899-1948, n.d., (4 folders) (Box 88)
    - B, 1896-1951, n.d., (7 folders) (Box 88)
    - C, 1896-1937, n.d., (7 folders) (Box 88)
    - D, 1896-1948, n.d., (5 folders) (Box 89)
    - E, 1913-1940, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 89)
    - F, 1898-1950, n.d., (4 folders) (Box 89)
    - G, 1896-1948, n.d., (7 folders) (Box 89)
    - H, 1895-1920, n.d., (4 folders) (Box 89)
    - H, 1921-1951, (4 folders) (Box 90)
    - I, 1912-1937, n.d. (Box 90)
    - J, 1910-1927, 1932-1937, 1950, n.d., (4 folders) (Box 90)
    - K, 1893-1951, n.d., (5 folders) (Box 90)
    - L, 1905-1948, n.d., (6 folders) (Box 90)
    - M, 1896-1918, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 90)
    - M, 1919-1956, n.d., (9 folders) (Box 91)
    - N, 1899-1949, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 91)
    - O, 1909-1947, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 91)
    - P, 1901-1952, n.d., (5 folders) (Box 91)
    - Q, 1919-1946, n.d. (Box 91)
    - R, 1899-1918, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 91)
    - R, 1919-1952, (4 folders) (Box 92)
    - S, 1895-1951, n.d., (13 folders) (Box 92)
    - T, 1893-1949, (5 folders) (Box 93)
    - U, 1914-1950, n.d. (Box 93)
    - V, 1913-1932, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 93)
    - W, 1894-1951, n.d., (12 folders) (Box 93)
    - Y, 1912-1946, n.d. (Box 93)
    - Z, 1917-1947, n.d. (Box 93)
    - Illegible signatures, 1894-1929, n.d. (Box 93)
  - Letterpress Books, 1909-1913, 1.3:
    This subseries contains twelve volumes of letterpress books of outgoing letters from Macbeth Gallery dated 1909 to 1913. Each volume begins with an alphabetical list of names of recipients; each recipient's name is followed by a list of page numbers indicating the pages in the volume on which copies of letters to that recipient can be found.
    The volumes are arranged chronologically.
    - Volume 1 (NMc68:1-502), June 1909-January 1910 (Box 94)
    - Volume 2 (NMc68:503-1032), January-May 1910 (Box 94)
    - Volume 3 (NMc69:1033-1772), May-December 1910 (Box 94)
    - Volume 4 (NMc69:1773-2281), December 1910-February 1911 (Box 94)
    - Volume 5 (NMc70:2282-2794), February 1911-April 1911 (Box 94)
    - Volume 6 (NMc70:2795-3303), April-September 1911 (Box 94)
    - Volume 7 (NMc70:3304-3462/NMc71: 3463-3812), September-December 1911 (Box 95)
    - Volume 8 (NMc71:3813-4319), December 1911-March 1912 (Box 95)
    - Volume 9 (NMc71:4320-4670), March-May 1912 (Box 95)
    - Volume 10 (NMc72:4671-5354), May-November 1912 (Box 95)
    - Volume 11 (NMc72:5355-5967), November 1912-February 1913 (Box 95)
    - Volume 12 (NMc73:5968-6396), February-May 1913 (Box 95)
- Financial and Shipping Records, 1892-1956, Series 2:; (Box 96-110; 11.8 linear feet)
  This series provides a detailed record of the gallery's financial transactions through a variety of ledgers and account books. Although they lack systematic indexing and are somewhat awkward to use, these records provide an intriguing insight into art buying and collecting tendencies throughout the first half of the twentieth century. They also record the effect of fluctuations in the economy including, of course, the devastating Depression of the 1930s. Records in this series can be used more effectively in conjunction with the card files in Series 3: Inventory Records.
  A large account book found here contains records dating from ca. 1918 to the 1930s with entries arranged alphabetically by the name of the person, corporate body or function (such as "Accrued Salaries") to which each account applies. The book lists the dates and descriptions of transactions along with debits, credits and balances on accounts. Each alphabetical letter group is preceded by an index of accounts that fall in that section of the alphabet.
  Information regarding commissions and commission credits due to artists, businesses or individuals is recorded in three sets of volumes: Artist Credit Books; Purchase Books and Commission Credits; and Artist Commissions, Commission Credits and Purchases. Artist Commissions, Commission Credits and Purchases combine information that was previously contained in the other two types of ledgers. Details of purchases and commissions are arranged chronologically. There are also two unidentified volumes filed here as Artist Registers which appear to record information related to framing dating from ca. 1924 to 1954. The registers are arranged chronologically and then list artists as well as titles and dimensions of artwork and dates received.
  Bills and statements consist of copies of outgoing bills and statements from the gallery and are arranged chronologically by year and alphabetically within those years
  Cash Books provide a chronological list of cash transactions and Charge Books, also known as "Order Books" and "Sales Books," contain lists of charges for merchandise and order registers and are arranged chronologically. Miscellaneous incoming bills are arranged chronologically by year and alphabetically by client within each year. Many of the bills were previously folded together with brown paper labels which have been transferred to the folders preceding the records to which they apply.
  One item of particular note is a small untitled notebook summarizing annual sales figures from 1892 to 1935. The notebook clearly shows the ongoing economic collapse of the 1930s with annual sales plummeting from $487,283.62 in 1929 to $92,659.02 in 1933.
  The series also contains records of conisgnments from 1933 to 1951 and shipping records from the 1930s to the 1950s.
  In general, financial records are arranged chronologically and then alphabetically by client.
  - Account Book, ca. 1918-1930s (Box 96)
  - Artist Commissions, Commission Credits and Purchases, 1930-1950, (2 volumes) (Box 97 (sol))
  - Artist Credit Books, 1892-1930, (5 volumes) (Box 98 (hol))
  - Artist Registers, ca. 1924-1954, (2 volumes) (Box 107 (sol))
  - Balance Sheets, 1954, 1955 (Box 99)
  - Bills and Statements, 1909-1914, (2 volumes) (Box 99)
  - Bills and Statements, 1915-1920, (12 folders) (Box 99)
  - Bills and Statements, 1921-1927, (11 folders) (Box 100)
  - Bills and Statements, 1929-1932, (12 folders) (Box 101)
  - Bills and Statements, 1934, 1945-1952, (14 folders) (Box 102)
  - Cash Books, 1895-1909, (4 volumes) (Box 103 (hol))
  - Cash Books, 1910-1934, 1943-1951, (12 volumes) (Box 104)
  - Charge ("Order") Books, 1892-1909, (7 volumes) (Box 105)
  - Charge ("Order") Books, 1910-1931, (5 volumes) (Box 106)
  - Charge ("Order") Books, 1931-1941 (Box 107 (sol))
  - Consignment Book, 1933-1951 (Box 108 (hol))
  - Journals, 1904-1909, 1918-1929, (2 volumes) (Box 108 (hol))
  - Miscellaneous Incoming Bills, 1920-1935, (17 folders) (Box 109)
  - Miscellaneous Insurance Cards, 1936-1953 (Box 109)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, ca. 1896-1956, (2 folders) (Box 109)
  - Monthly Sales Books, 1905-1913 (Box 109)
  - Petty Cash Book, 1927-1931 (Box 110)
  - Purchase Books and Commission Credits, 1910-1930, (6 volumes) (Box 110)
  - Shipping Ledgers, Incoming Express and Parcel Post, 1936-1950 (Box 110)
  - Shipping Ledgers, Local Temporary Incoming, 1936-1943 (Box 110)
  - Shipping Ledgers, Local Temporary Outgoing, 1936-1949 (Box 110)
  - Shipping Ledgers, Outgoing Express, 1933-1953, (2 volumes) (Box 110)
  - Tax Book, 1919-1938 (Box 110)
  - Untitled Notebook of Annual Sales Figures, 1892-1935 (Box 110)
- Inventory Records, 1892-ca. 1957, Series 3:; (Box 111-113; 3.0 linear feet)
  The information found here supports that found in Series 2: Financial and Shipping Records and consists of card files recording stock disposition and a series of stock books. The card files are an invaluable tool for tracking the artwork that passed through Macbeth's hands. The first file, arranged alphabetically by artist, records the disposition of all pictures sold and unsold and the second, arranged by buyer, provides similar information from a different angle. The cards record information such as inventory numbers, names of artists, titles of pictures, dates received, media, sizes, framing information, owners, and sales prices. Some cards have photographs of pictures attached.
  While most of the stock books list gallery stock only, those for 1894-1903 and 1906 contain a record of pictures which were the property of William Macbeth, and for which he assumed liability in the event of loss or damage by, or resulting from fire.
  - Card Files (Box 111)
    - Pictures Unsold, A - F (Reel 2820), 1892-ca. 1957 (Box 111)
    - Pictures Unsold, F, cont. - H (Reel 2820-2821), 1892-ca. 1957 (Box 111)
    - Pictures Unsold, I - P (Reel 2821), 1892-ca. 1957 (Box 111)
    - Pictures Unsold, Q-R (Reel 2821)- Pictures Sold, A - G (Reel 2822), 1892-ca. 1957 (Box 111)
    - Pictures Sold, H - P (Reel 2822), 1892-ca. 1957 (Box 112)
    - Pictures Sold, Q-Z (Reels 2822-2823), Buyers, A-Z, 1892-ca. 1957 (Box 112)
  - Stock Book, 1892-1897 (Box 113)
  - Stock Book, 1897-1900 (Box 113)
  - Stock Book, 1894-1903 (Box 113)
  - Stock Book, 1901-1902 (Box 113)
  - Stock Book, 1903-1906 (Box 113)
  - Stock Book, 1903-1905 (Box 113)
  - Stock Book, 1906 (Box 113)
  - Stock Book, 1906-1909 (Box 113)
- Printed Material, 1838-1963, n.d., Series 4:; (Box 114-119, 162; 5.0 linear feet)
  This series contains printed material published by Macbeth Gallery in addition to exhibition catalogs from other galleries and organizations, art publications, and loose magazine articles and news clippings.
  The series is organized two subseries:
  4.1: Macbeth Gallery Printed Material, 1862-1963, n.d.
  4.2: Other Printed Material, 1838-1962, n.d.
  - Macbeth Gallery Printed Material, 1862-1963, n.d., 4.1:
    This subseries contains the Macbeth Gallery publications Art Notes and Biographical Notes in addition to scattered exhibition announcements, catalogs and news clippings. The bulk of the news clippings in the collection and the gallery's exhibition catalogs can be found in Series 5: Scrapbooks.
    Art Notes was an occasional publication issued during the art season "in the Interest of American Art and the Macbeth Gallery" from 1896 to 1930. The booklets typically contain essays on artists, current exhibitions at the gallery and current events in the art world and are an excellent source of information on the history of the gallery until 1930 and the opinions of the owners on various artistic trends and movements. Of particular note is an essay criticizing the Modernist movement which received attention in the press as well as letters, primarily of support, from many of the gallery's clients. Most of the issues are in bound voumes although there are also some individual copies of the publication. Numbers 14 and 24 are missing. Judging by the number of requests for Art Notes in the Series 1: Correspondence, it was an extremely popular publication, especially with those who artistic tastes tended toward the conservative.
    Also found here is the publication Biographical Notes, a collection of short biographies of fifty artists "whose reputations and experience of over twenty years enables us to vouch with some degree of certainty." The publication was intended to satisfy "the natural curiosity of the picture collector to know who the man is who painted the picture, and what he has done in the past that may indicate his position in the future."
    Several of the exhibition announcements and catalogs found here are annotated and some are accompanied by news clippings. Catalogs include those for the gallery's fiftieth and sixtieth anniversaries. One catalog for an exhibition organized and circulated by the American Federation of Arts in conjunction with the Archives of American Art is included here because it documented the role of the Macbeth Gallery. The catalog contains an essay written by Robert G. McIntyre for the exhibition entitled "The Macbeth Gallery: A Capsule History."
    Also found here is a folder of six scattered news clippings recording milestones in the gallery's history such as the move to 15 East Fifty-seventh Street and the gallery's fiftieth and sixtieth anniversaries. At the end of the series is a box of duplicate copies of Art Notes.
    - Art Notes Nos. 1-12, October 1896-February 1900 (Box 114 (hol))
    - Art Notes Nos. 13, 15-23, April 1900-November 1903 (Box 114 (hol))
    - Art Notes Nos. 25-36, May 1904-December 1908 (Box 114 (hol))
    - Art Notes Nos. 37-48, March 1909-April 1913 (Box 114 (hol))
    - Art Notes Nos. 49-60, November 1913-May 1916 (Box 114 (hol))
    - Art Notes Nos. 61-73, November 1916-October/November 1921 (Box 114 (hol))
    - Art Notes Nos. 74-85, January/February 1922-June 1927 (Box 114 (hol))
    - Art Notes Nos. 86-88, November 1928, November 1929, November, 1930 (Box 114 (hol))
    - Biographical Notes, 1915 (Box 115 (pam))
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1914-1952, n.d., (7 folders) (Box 115 (pam))
    - Exhibition Catalog, From the Archives of American Art: The Role of the Macbeth Gallery, 1962-1963 (Box 115 (pam))
    - News Clippings, 1932-1952, n.d. (Box 115 (pam))
    - Duplicate Copies of Art Notes (Box 162)
  - Other Printed Material, 1838-1962, n.d., 4.2:
    These folders contain non-Macbeth Gallery printed material including magazine and newspaper articles on a variety of artists as well as exhibition announcements and catalogs from other galleries, museums, and organizations including the American Water Color Society and the National Academy of Design.
    One item of particular note is a bound catalog of the exhibition Ten American Painters held at the Durand-Ruel, Inc., in 1898. The catalog is signed by each of the ten painters represented in the exhibition.
    Also of note among the art publications is a set of bound volumes of the pre-Civil War American art journal The Crayon. Published monthly in New York The Crayon was the first substantial periodical devoted entirely to the arts and is an indispensable resource for research on developments in the art world of the immediate pre-Civil War period. The volumes comprise an almost complete run of the journal which was published between 1855 and 1861. The Macbeth Gallery set dates from 1855 to 1859.
    At the end of the series are two delightful pamphlets concerning Frederick Keppel's relationship with James MacNeill Whistler. The first was "privately printed and copyrighted by Frederick Keppel" in 1904 and entitled The Gentle Art of Resenting Injuries, some "unpublished correspondence addressed to the author of "The Gentle Art of Making Enemies." The second is entitled "One Day With Whistler," published by Keppel in 1908. The first booklet describes an altercation between Keppel and Whistler in the form of reprinted correspondence between the two men and Keppel's commentary on the incident which he describes as a "brilliant specimen of characteristic abusive Whistlerism." There are two copies of the pamphlet, which Keppel published in "very limited edition" solely for a few of his friends, one addressed to "To Robert W. Macbeth from his friend-the author," and another to William Macbeth. The second pamphlet further describes "Whistler's intercourse with me and mine with him."
    - Catalog and Magazine Clippings, 1925-1958, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 116)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1839-1962, n.d., (8 folders) (Box 116)
    - Exhibition Catalogs (Box 116)
      - American Water Color Society, 1884, 1887, 1888, 1891, (4 folders) (Box 116)
      - National Academy of Design, 1838-1884, (4 folders) (Box 116)
      - Ten American Painters, 1898 (Box 116)